Guide to the Ernst Cohen Photograph Collection 1964-2002 PR 280
New-York Historical Society
Ernst Cohen photograph collection
1964-2002
New-York Historical Society
Cohen, Ernst, 1923-2009.
PR 280
0.5 Linear feet
The Ernst Cohen Photograph Collection consists of approximately 400 black and white photographs of Manhattan from 1964 thru 2002, with the bulk of the images from the 1990's. In addition to street scenes that document New Yorkers going about everyday life, Cohen photographed a number of special events, including parades (Gay Pride, St. Patrick's Day, Turkish Day, and others), a Russ Perot rally, and various street fairs. Cohen's style reflects the documentary small-format camera street photography tradition popular during the 1960's and 70's in the United States with photographers such as Gary Winogrand and Robert Frank.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Elizabeth Cohan, 2009.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series.
Series I. Events includes street images of people at various events such as ethnic and holiday parades, street fairs, political rallies and demonstrations.
Series II. Cityscapes includes well-known streets, neighborhoods, public spaces, and candid shots of the people using them, as well as skyline photos.
Series III. Personal Photographs includes one photographs of Cohen and several photos of his Brooklyn Heights apartment.
Biographical Note
Ernst Cohen (1923-2009) was an amateur photographer who lived in Brooklyn, New York for most of his life. He was born in Berlin, Germany, to David (Yitzhak) Cohen and Sarah Littmann Cohen. His father was a well known Cantor at a large synagogue in Berlin. In 1939, just before the outbreak of WWII, his parents sent Ernst and his brother to live with his mother's half sister, Clara Hirsch, and her husband, a physician in Brooklyn. Tragically, he never saw his parents again, for they were imprisoned and killed at Auschwitz in 1942.
After graduating from City University of New York, Ernst became a long-time employee of the Social Security Administration. He developed an interest in photography while still in high school, using an old pre-war Leica camera to shoot portraits and street scenes in Manhattan and Brooklyn. Eventually, he created a darkroom in his Brooklyn Heights apartment and developed his own negatives and prints.
Never married, Ernst Cohen bequeathed the contents of his apartment to his friend and neighbor, Elizabeth Cohan, who offered his photographs to the New-York Historical Society and the Brooklyn Historical Society. Ms. Cohan also provided the biographical information for this finding aide in an oral interview as well as a short written biography, a copy of which is located in the Print Room collection files.
Related Materials
The Brooklyn Historical Society holds a small collection of Ernst Cohen's photographs of Brooklyn, accessioned at the same time as this collection.
Scope and Contents
The Ernst Cohen Photograph Collection consists of approximately 400 black and white photographs of Manhattan from 1964 thru 2002, with the bulk of the images from the 1990's. In addition to street scenes that document New Yorkers going about everyday life, Cohen photographed a number of special events, including parades (Gay Pride, St. Patrick's Day, Turkish Day, and others), a Russ Perot rally, and various street fairs. Cohen's style reflects the documentary small-format camera street photography tradition popular during the 1960's and 70's in the United States with photographers such as Gary Winogrand and Robert Frank.
Gelatin silver prints.; Photographic prints.; Snapshots; Billboards; Buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Children -- New York (State) -- New York.; Exhibition buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Graffiti.; Parades -- New York (State) -- New York.; Political rallies; Street photography.; Columbus Circle (New York, N.Y.); Little Italy (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Times Square (New York, N.Y.); Union Square (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I. Events, 1964-1999; 0.5 Linear feet
  - Subseries I. Parades, 1964-1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Columbus Day Parade, 1996, 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Easter Parade, 1973 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Gay Pride Parade, 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Latin American Day Parade, 1996 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - St. Patricks Day Parades, 1997, 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Steuben Day Parade, 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Turkish Day Parade, 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified parade, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7A)
  - Subseries II. Street Fairs, 1992-1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lower Broadway Fair, 1996 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Water Street Fair, 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ninth Avenue Food Fair, 1996 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lower East Side Fair, 1996 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified, unknown (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Subseries III. Political Rallies and Demonstrations, circa 1990-1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dinkins/Green Political Rally, 1993 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ross Perot Voter Registration Drive, circa 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Anti Nudity Demonstration, unknown (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Gay Rights Demonstration, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II. Cityscapes
  - Subseries I. Skylines and Vistas
    - Harbor Views, 1975-2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    - Aerial Views, 1964-circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Subseries II. Named Streets, 1990's
    - Catherine and Broadway (2), 1996 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - Chambers Street and Broadway, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - Orchard Street (3), circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - Grand Street (2), circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - West Houston and Broadway, circa 1990's (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - St. Marks Place (4), circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Subseries III: Numbered Streets and Avenues, 1990's
    - West 8th Street (2), 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - West 48th Street, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - 4th Avenue near Astor Place (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Fifth Avenue - Midtown (11), 1994-1996 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - 6th Avenue and 18-19th Streets (3) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Avenue of the Americas - Midtown (2), circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries IV. Parks, Circles and Squares, 1964-1995
    - Central Park (13), 1965-1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    - Columbus Circle, 1964 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    - Union Square (3), 1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    - Times Square (7), circa 1990-1993 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Subseries V. Neighborhoods, 1991-1998
    - South Street Seaport (5), 1996 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    - Little Italy (2), circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    - Chinatown (20), 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subseries VI. Street Scenes (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - People, circa 1970 - 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Transportation, 1964, 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
    - Graffiti and Billboards (10), 1964-2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Subseries VII. Buildings, 1964-2002
    - Kabbalah Learning Center (E. 48th Street), circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - Avenue B Movie Theater (2), circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - 2 Columbus Circle, 1964 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - Lincoln Center (2), 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - The Julliard School, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - Bank of the Metropolis, 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - St. Patrick's Cathedral (2), 1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - New York Public Library (3), 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - Pan Am Building from W. 44th St., unknown (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad Station (2), 1964-1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - 492 Broome Street, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - Municipal Building/interior and exterior (3), circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - Castle Williams - Governor's Island, 2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - Surrogate's Court, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - New York State Supreme Court, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - Woolworth Building Front Entrance - color, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - 2 Broadway - Stone to Beaver Streets - color, 1964 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
  - Subseries VIII. Storefronts and Businesses
    - Manny's Music, 1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Olde Good Things, circa 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Papaya King, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Canal Jean Company, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Wig City-The Brew Burger-Income Tax Preparation Co., circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Frank Perro Bail Bonds-Talt Steno Service-Dispossesses Law Office, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - BiWay, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Think Soho (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - FAO Schwarz, 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Modell's at Chambers Street - color, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Wah Wing Sang Funeral Corp. - color (2), circa 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
- Series III. Personal Photographs
  - Interior of photographer's apartment (5), unknown (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Ernst Cohen - color photo, unknown (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)